<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Electronics-1 on Atharva Phadke</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/electronics/11th/electronics-1/</link><description>Recent content in Electronics-1 on Atharva Phadke</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>CC BY-NC 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 22:44:41 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/electronics/11th/electronics-1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Study of Resistors</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-resistors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 05:13:36 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-resistors/</guid><description>Study Of Resistors Basic Resistor Diagram: A basic resistor. Part 1: Study of Resistors Aim The aim of this section is to provide a comprehensive understanding of resistors, their components, equipments, and types.
Components List Resistor Multimeter Equipments Power Supply Breadboard Types Of Resistors Fixed Resistors Variable Resistors Information about Fixed Resistors Fixed resistors are electrical components that have a fixed value of resistance, meaning that their resistance does not change.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="study-of-resistors">Study Of Resistors</h1>
<figure><img src="/img/resistor.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>Basic Resistor</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="diagram-a-basic-resistor">Diagram: A basic resistor.</h3>
<h2 id="part-1-study-of-resistors">Part 1: Study of Resistors</h2>
<h3 id="aim">Aim</h3>
<p>The aim of this section is to provide a comprehensive understanding of resistors, their components, equipments, and types.</p>
<h3 id="components-list">Components List</h3>
<ol>
<li>Resistor</li>
<li>Multimeter</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="equipments">Equipments</h3>
<ol>
<li>Power Supply</li>
<li>Breadboard</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="types-of-resistors">Types Of Resistors</h3>
<ol>
<li>Fixed Resistors</li>
<li>Variable Resistors</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="information-about-fixed-resistors">Information about Fixed Resistors</h3>
<p>Fixed resistors are electrical components that have a fixed value of resistance, meaning that their resistance does not change. This type of resistor is commonly used to limit the current flow in a circuit and to divide voltage.</p>
<h3 id="information-about-different-types-of-fixed-resistors">Information about different types of Fixed Resistors</h3>
<ol>
<li>Carbon Film Resistor: These resistors are made by depositing a thin layer of carbon on a cylindrical ceramic or plastic form. They are the most common type of fixed resistor and offer a low cost solution with a relatively high resistance tolerance.</li>
<li>Metal Film Resistor: These resistors are made by depositing a thin layer of metal on a cylindrical ceramic or plastic form. They offer improved resistance tolerance compared to carbon film resistors and are more stable.</li>
<li>Wire Wound Resistor: These resistors are made by winding a wire, typically made of nickel-chromium alloy, around a cylindrical form. They offer high power handling capabilities and precise resistance values, making them suitable for use in high-power applications.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="resistor-colour-coding">Resistor Colour Coding</h3>
<p><img src="https://www.te.com/content/dam/te-com/images/corporate/marketing/global/infographics/resistor-color-code-bands-3-4-1024.png" alt="Resistor Colour Coding"></p>
<h3 id="information-about-variable-resistors">Information about Variable Resistors</h3>
<p>Variable resistors, also known as potentiometers, allow the resistance value to be adjusted. They are commonly used in applications where the resistance value needs to be changed, such as volume control in a stereo system.</p>
<h3 id="information-about-different-types-of-variable-resistors">Information about different types of Variable Resistors</h3>
<ol>
<li>Potentiometer: A potentiometer is a three-terminal resistor where the resistance between two terminals can be adjusted using a sliding contact known as a wiper.</li>
<li>Rheostat: A rheostat is a two-terminal resistor where the resistance can be adjusted using a sliding contact. Rheostats are typically used to control the current flow in a circuit.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="part-2-potential-divider-arrangement">Part 2: Potential divider arrangement</h2>
<h3 id="aim-1">Aim</h3>
<p>The aim of this section is to study the potential divider arrangement in detail and understand its applications in electronics.</p>
<h3 id="components-list-1">Components List</h3>
<ol>
<li>Resistor</li>
<li>Voltage Source</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="equipments-1">Equipments</h3>
<ol>
<li>Breadboard</li>
<li>Multimeter</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="explain-theory-in-deep">Explain theory in deep</h3>
<p>In a potential divider arrangement, two resistors are connected in series to a voltage source. The voltage across each resistor is proportional to its resistance, with the voltage across the first resistor (R1) being Vout and the voltage across the second resistor (R2) being (Vin - Vout). By knowing the voltage across the resistors, the resistance values can be calculated using Ohm&rsquo;s law, which states that the current in a circuit is equal to the voltage divided by the resistance.</p>
<h3 id="diagram">Diagram</h3>
<p><img src="https://qph.cf2.quoracdn.net/main-qimg-3ada7a203f51881e291de1e7d67daa99" alt="Potential divider arrangement diagram"></p>
<h3 id="formula-for-potential-divider-arrangement">Formula for potential divider arrangement</h3>
<p>Vout = (R2/(R1 + R2)) * Vin</p>
<h3 id="example">Example</h3>
<p>Given Vin = 10V and R1 = 2kΩ and R2 = 4kΩ, find Vout.</p>
<p>Vout = (R2/(R1 + R2)) * Vin
Vout = (4kΩ/(2kΩ + 4kΩ)) * 10V
Vout = (4kΩ/6kΩ) * 10V
Vout = (2/3) * 10V
Vout = 6.67V</p>
<p>For Notes, and practical images, refer this:
<a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/11ARyTZphPKpo9fPhy97rB0HLTRN2Exp5?usp=sharing"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Drive-Folder-green" alt="GDrive Folder"></a></p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>In this study, we have covered the basics of resistors, including their components, types, and the potential divider arrangement. Understanding resistors and their behavior is crucial in many electrical and electronics applications.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Construction of Ce Amp on Breadboard</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-ce-amp-on-breadboard/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:31:48 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-ce-amp-on-breadboard/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Construction of Multivibrator Ckt on Pcb</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multivibrator-ckt-on-pcb/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:31:25 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multivibrator-ckt-on-pcb/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Construction of Fbr With Filter</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-fbr-with-filter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:30:59 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-fbr-with-filter/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Loading Effect of Voltmeter</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/loading-effect-of-voltmeter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:29:52 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/loading-effect-of-voltmeter/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Construction of Multirange Ammeter</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multirange-ammeter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:29:33 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multirange-ammeter/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Construction of Multirange Voltmeter</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multirange-voltmeter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:29:22 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multirange-voltmeter/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Sinusoidal Non Sinusoidal Waveforms on Cro</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-sinusoidal-non-sinusoidal-waveforms-on-cro/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:28:58 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-sinusoidal-non-sinusoidal-waveforms-on-cro/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Mpt Theorem</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/mpt-theorem/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:28:20 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/mpt-theorem/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Thevenin's Theorem</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-thevenins-theorem/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:54 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-thevenins-theorem/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Transformer</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-transformer/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:35 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-transformer/</guid><description>Summary A transformer is a passive electrical component that transfers electrical energy from one circuit to another through electromagnetic induction. In this study, we will learn about the construction and working of a basic transformer, different types of transformers, and their applications. We will also learn about the parts required to make a basic transformer and the instruments and equipment needed to perform this activity.
Basic Transformer Parts and Specifications A basic transformer consists of the following parts:</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>A transformer is a passive electrical component that transfers electrical energy from one circuit to another through electromagnetic induction. In this study, we will learn about the construction and working of a basic transformer, different types of transformers, and their applications. We will also learn about the parts required to make a basic transformer and the instruments and equipment needed to perform this activity.</p>
<figure><img src="/img/transformer.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>Basic Transformer</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="parts-and-specifications">Parts and Specifications</h2>
<p>A basic transformer consists of the following parts:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Parts</th>
<th>Specifications</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Copper Wire</td>
<td>Number of turns and gauge depends on the desired voltage and current rating</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Iron Core</td>
<td>Magnetic permeability and cross-sectional area depends on the desired inductance</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Insulating Material</td>
<td>High voltage insulation to prevent current from leaking from one coil to another</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="instruments-and-equipment">Instruments and Equipment</h2>
<p>The following instruments and equipment are required to perform this activity:</p>
<ul>
<li>Soldering iron</li>
<li>Wire cutter</li>
<li>Insulating tape</li>
<li>Multimeter</li>
<li>Power supply</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="procedure">Procedure</h2>
<p>The procedure to make a simple transformer is as follows:</p>
<ol>
<li>Cut two pieces of copper wire to the desired length, with the number of turns and gauge depending on the desired voltage and current rating.</li>
<li>Wrap the two pieces of wire around an iron core, with the magnetic permeability and cross-sectional area depending on the desired inductance.</li>
<li>Insulate the two coils from each other using insulating material to prevent current from leaking from one coil to another.</li>
<li>Solder the two ends of each coil to its own terminal.</li>
<li>Test the transformer using a multimeter to measure the voltage and current ratings.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="theory">Theory</h2>
<p>The basic theory behind a transformer is electromagnetic induction. When an alternating current flows through one coil, it generates a magnetic field that induces a voltage in the other coil. The voltage is proportional to the number of turns in each coil, the frequency of the alternating current, and the magnetic permeability of the core.</p>
<h2 id="types-of-transformers">Types of Transformers</h2>
<p>There are several types of transformers, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Step-Up Transformer: Increases the voltage of the alternating current</li>
<li>Step-Down Transformer: Decreases the voltage of the alternating current</li>
<li>Isolation Transformer: Electrically isolates the two coils from each other, while still allowing energy transfer</li>
<li>Auto Transformer: A type of transformer that uses a single winding instead of two separate windings</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="uses-of-transformers">Uses of Transformers</h2>
<p>Transformers are widely used in electrical power distribution systems to step up or step down the voltage of the alternating current, according to the requirements of the load. They are also used in electronic devices such as televisions, radios, and computers, to provide isolation and regulation of the power supply.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In conclusion, transformers play a crucial role in electrical power distribution and regulation. Understanding the construction, theory, and types of transformers is essential for anyone involved in electrical engineering and design. By performing the procedure described in this study, one can gain practical experience in building a basic transformer and gain a deeper understanding of this fascinating component.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Study of Relay</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-relay/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-relay/</guid><description>Summary This topic aims to provide an in-depth understanding of relays, including their construction, working principle, and various applications.
Construction of a Basic Relay A basic relay consists of an electromagnet, a set of contacts, and a spring. When the electromagnet is energized, it attracts the armature, which then moves and closes the contacts.
Diagram:
Basic Relay Parts and Specifications Parts Specifications Electromagnet Consists of a coil of wire, core, and a switch Contacts Typically made of metal and used to complete or break an electrical circuit Armature A movable piece of metal that is attracted by the electromagnet and responsible for closing the contacts Spring Used to return the armature to its original position when the electromagnet is de-energized Instruments and Tools Needed Multimeter Oscilloscope Soldering iron Wire stripper Pliers Procedure Start by gathering all the necessary parts and tools.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>This topic aims to provide an in-depth understanding of relays, including their construction, working principle, and various applications.</p>
<h2 id="construction-of-a-basic-relay">Construction of a Basic Relay</h2>
<p>A basic relay consists of an electromagnet, a set of contacts, and a spring. When the electromagnet is energized, it attracts the armature, which then moves and closes the contacts.</p>
<p>Diagram:</p>
<figure><img src="/img/relay.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>Basic Relay</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="parts-and-specifications">Parts and Specifications</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Parts</th>
<th>Specifications</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Electromagnet</td>
<td>Consists of a coil of wire, core, and a switch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Contacts</td>
<td>Typically made of metal and used to complete or break an electrical circuit</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Armature</td>
<td>A movable piece of metal that is attracted by the electromagnet and responsible for closing the contacts</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Spring</td>
<td>Used to return the armature to its original position when the electromagnet is de-energized</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="instruments-and-tools-needed">Instruments and Tools Needed</h2>
<ul>
<li>Multimeter</li>
<li>Oscilloscope</li>
<li>Soldering iron</li>
<li>Wire stripper</li>
<li>Pliers</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="procedure">Procedure</h2>
<ol>
<li>Start by gathering all the necessary parts and tools.</li>
<li>Assemble the electromagnet by winding the coil of wire around the core and soldering the leads to the switch.</li>
<li>Mount the armature, contacts, and spring in their respective positions.</li>
<li>Test the relay using a multimeter to verify that the contacts are opening and closing correctly when the electromagnet is energized and de-energized.</li>
<li>Measure the voltage and current required to operate the relay using an oscilloscope.</li>
<li>Finally, connect the relay to a circuit and test it under normal operating conditions.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="theory">Theory</h2>
<p>Relays are electrical switches that use an electromagnet to operate. When a voltage is applied to the coil of the electromagnet, it creates a magnetic field that attracts the armature, causing it to close the contacts. This closing of contacts completes the electrical circuit and allows current to flow. When the voltage is removed from the coil, the magnetic field collapses, and the spring returns the armature to its original position, opening the contacts and breaking the circuit.</p>
<p>Relays are useful in controlling high-power circuits with low-power signals, as well as in protecting sensitive electronic circuits from damage due to overloading.</p>
<h2 id="applications">Applications</h2>
<p>Relays find applications in a wide range of fields, including automotive electronics, communication systems, industrial control systems, and home appliances. Some common applications of relays include controlling the operation of motors, switching on and off lights, and providing over-current protection to sensitive electronic circuits.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In conclusion, relays are an essential component in electrical and electronic circuits. They provide a simple and effective way to control and protect high-power circuits with low-power signals. Understanding the construction, working principle, and applications of relays is essential for anyone working in the field of electrical and electronics engineering.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Study of Switches</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-switches/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:19 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-switches/</guid><description>Summary A switch is a crucial component in electrical circuits as it can control the flow of electricity by making or breaking a connection. In this topic, we will study the basic construction, different types of switches, the function and purpose of switches, the tools and equipment required to demonstrate a basic switch, and more.
Diagram Basic Switch Diagram: A figure showing a Basic Switch &amp;amp; its states
Parts and Specifications Parts Specifications Switch SPST, SPDT, DPST, DPDT Wires 20-22 gauge Breadboard Half-sized breadboard Tools and Equipment Breadboard Jumper Wires Power Supply Multimeter Procedure To demonstrate a basic switch, follow these steps:</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>A switch is a crucial component in electrical circuits as it can control the flow of electricity by making or breaking a connection. In this topic, we will study the basic construction, different types of switches, the function and purpose of switches, the tools and equipment required to demonstrate a basic switch, and more.</p>
<h2 id="diagram">Diagram</h2>
<figure><img src="/img/switch.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>Basic Switch</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>Diagram: A figure showing a Basic Switch &amp; its states</strong></p>
<h2 id="parts-and-specifications">Parts and Specifications</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Parts</th>
<th>Specifications</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Switch</td>
<td>SPST, SPDT, DPST, DPDT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Wires</td>
<td>20-22 gauge</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Breadboard</td>
<td>Half-sized breadboard</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="tools-and-equipment">Tools and Equipment</h2>
<ul>
<li>Breadboard</li>
<li>Jumper Wires</li>
<li>Power Supply</li>
<li>Multimeter</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="procedure">Procedure</h2>
<p>To demonstrate a basic switch, follow these steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>Gather all the required parts and tools mentioned above.</li>
<li>Connect the power supply to the breadboard.</li>
<li>Connect one end of the switch to the power supply on the breadboard and the other end to the load (e.g., LED or buzzer).</li>
<li>Use the multimeter to measure the resistance and verify that the switch is open.</li>
<li>Close the switch by pressing the button and verify that the resistance is zero.</li>
<li>Observe that the load is now powered on, indicating that the switch has made a connection.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="theory">Theory</h2>
<p>A switch is an electrical component that can make or break an electrical connection. It is designed to control the flow of electricity in a circuit. There are several types of switches, including SPST (Single Pole Single Throw), SPDT (Single Pole Double Throw), DPST (Double Pole Single Throw), and DPDT (Double Pole Double Throw).</p>
<h2 id="types-of-switches">Types of Switches</h2>
<figure><img src="/img/spst.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>SPST Switch</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="spst-single-pole-single-throw-switches-have-a-single-contact-that-can-either-be-connected-or-disconnected-it-is-the-simplest-type-of-switch">SPST (Single Pole Single Throw) switches have a single contact that can either be connected or disconnected. It is the simplest type of switch.</h3>
<figure><img src="/img/spdt.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>SPDT Switch</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="spdt-single-pole-double-throw-switches-have-two-contacts-and-can-switch-between-two-separate-circuits-it-is-commonly-used-for-switch-selector-applications">SPDT (Single Pole Double Throw) switches have two contacts and can switch between two separate circuits. It is commonly used for switch-selector applications.</h3>
<figure><img src="/img/dpst.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>DPST Switch</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="dpst-double-pole-single-throw-switches-have-two-separate-contacts-that-can-either-be-connected-or-disconnected-simultaneously-this-type-of-switch-is-used-for-applications-where-two-separate-circuits-need-to-be-controlled-by-a-single-switch">DPST (Double Pole Single Throw) switches have two separate contacts that can either be connected or disconnected simultaneously. This type of switch is used for applications where two separate circuits need to be controlled by a single switch.</h3>
<figure><img src="/img/dpdt.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>DPDT Switch</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="dpdt-double-pole-double-throw-switches-have-two-separate-sets-of-contacts-that-can-switch-between-two-separate-circuits-it-is-commonly-used-for-reversing-switch-applications">DPDT (Double Pole Double Throw) switches have two separate sets of contacts that can switch between two separate circuits. It is commonly used for reversing switch applications.</h3>
<h2 id="uses-of-switches">Uses of Switches</h2>
<p>Switches play a crucial role in electrical circuits as they are used to control the flow of electricity. They are used in various applications such as turning on/off lights, controlling appliances, and in complex circuit designs such as computer motherboards, digital circuits, and more.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In conclusion, switches are essential components in electrical circuits as they control the flow of electricity. Understanding the basic construction, different types, functions, and uses of switches is important in electrical engineering. By demonstrating a basic switch, one can have a better</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Study of Inductors</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-inductors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:08 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-inductors/</guid><description>An inductor is a passive electrical component that stores energy in a magnetic field when electric current flows through it. Inductors play a crucial role in many electrical circuits, from filtering to energy storage to regulation. In this study, we will delve into the construction, theory, and uses of inductors.
Construction of a Basic Air-Core Inductor The basic air-core inductor can be constructed by wrapping a wire around a non-conductive core, such as air, plastic, or fiberglass.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An inductor is a passive electrical component that stores energy in a magnetic field when electric current flows through it. Inductors play a crucial role in many electrical circuits, from filtering to energy storage to regulation. In this study, we will delve into the construction, theory, and uses of inductors.</p>
<h2 id="construction-of-a-basic-air-core-inductor">Construction of a Basic Air-Core Inductor</h2>
<p>The basic air-core inductor can be constructed by wrapping a wire around a non-conductive core, such as air, plastic, or fiberglass. The number of turns, or coils, of wire used, along with the diameter and material of the wire, will determine the inductance of the inductor. To calculate the inductance, the formula <code>L = N^2 * Μ_o * A / l</code> can be used, where <code>N</code> is the number of turns, <code>Μ_o</code> is the permeability of free space, <code>A</code> is the cross-sectional area of the coil, and <code>l</code> is the length of the coil.</p>
<figure><img src="/img/inductor.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>Basic Inductor</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Diagram: A simple representation of an air-core inductor</p>
<h2 id="parts-and-specifications">Parts and Specifications</h2>
<p>The following table lists the parts and specifications needed to construct a basic air-core inductor:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Parts</th>
<th>Specifications</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Wire</td>
<td>Enameled copper wire with a diameter of 0.5 mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Core</td>
<td>Non-conductive material, such as air or plastic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Insulation tape</td>
<td>Electrical insulating tape to secure the ends of the wire</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="instruments-equipments-and-tools">Instruments, Equipments, and Tools</h2>
<p>To construct an air-core inductor, you will need the following instruments, equipments, and tools:</p>
<ul>
<li>A wire stripper</li>
<li>A spool of enameled copper wire</li>
<li>A non-conductive core, such as air or plastic</li>
<li>Electrical insulating tape</li>
<li>A ruler or measuring tape</li>
<li>A calculator</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="procedure">Procedure</h2>
<p>The procedure for constructing a basic air-core inductor involves wrapping a wire around a non-conductive core and securing the ends of the wire. The steps for this procedure are explained in detail below:</p>
<ol>
<li>Determine the desired inductance and calculate the number of turns required.</li>
<li>Cut a length of enameled copper wire to the desired length, plus an extra 10 cm for securing the ends.</li>
<li>Strip the insulation from the ends of the wire.</li>
<li>Wrap the wire around the non-conductive core to the desired number of turns.</li>
<li>Secure the ends of the wire with electrical insulating tape.</li>
<li>Test the inductance using a multimeter.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="theory">Theory</h2>
<p>An inductor is a passive electrical component that stores energy in a magnetic field when electric current flows through it. The basic principle behind an inductor is Faraday&rsquo;s Law of Electromagnetic Induction, which states that a changing magnetic field induces an electromotive force (EMF) in a conductor. The amount of energy stored in an inductor is proportional to the number of turns in the wire and the current flowing through it.</p>
<h2 id="types-of-cores">Types of Cores</h2>
<p>There are several different types of cores that can be used in inductors, including air cores, iron cores, ferrite cores, and more. Each type of core has its own unique properties and advantages, making it ideal for specific applications.</p>
<p>Air cores are the simplest and most basic type of inductor core, and are ideal for applications that require a large inductance. They are also the most economical and easiest to manufacture.</p>
<p>Iron cores are used for high-frequency applications and provide a higher magnetic permeability than air cores. They also allow for a more compact design, as the magnetic field is concentrated in the core.</p>
<p>Ferrite cores are made of a magnetic ceramic material and are often used in high-frequency applications where a high impedance is required. They are also immune to temperature changes, making them ideal for use in temperature-sensitive applications.</p>
<h3 id="uses-of-inductor">Uses of Inductor</h3>
<p>Inductors are widely used in electrical circuits for various purposes, including power supplies, filters, transformers, and resonant circuits.</p>
<p>One of the most common uses of inductors is in filters. Inductors are used in filter circuits to block or pass certain frequencies. A high-pass filter passes high-frequency signals and blocks low-frequency signals, while a low-pass filter passes low-frequency signals and blocks high-frequency signals.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>In conclusion, Inductors are important components in electrical circuits, and understanding their construction, parts, instruments, procedure, theory, types of cores, and uses is crucial. With this knowledge, one can effectively design and implement inductors in various electrical circuits.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Study of Capacitors</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-capacitors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-capacitors/</guid><description>Understanding Capacitors: A Study A capacitor is an electronic component that stores electrical energy in an electric field. Capacitors are widely used in electrical circuits for a variety of purposes, including filtering, coupling, and energy storage.
Diagram Basic Capacitor Diagram: Diagram of a basic capacitor
Types of Capacitors There are many different types of capacitors available, each with its own unique characteristics. Some common types include:
Aluminum electrolytic capacitors: These capacitors have a high capacitance and are commonly used in power supplies and audio equipment.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="understanding-capacitors-a-study">Understanding Capacitors: A Study</h1>
<p>A capacitor is an electronic component that stores electrical energy in an electric field. Capacitors are widely used in electrical circuits for a variety of purposes, including filtering, coupling, and energy storage.</p>
<h2 id="diagram">Diagram</h2>
<figure><img src="/img/capacitor.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>Basic Capacitor</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Diagram: Diagram of a basic capacitor</p>
<h2 id="types-of-capacitors">Types of Capacitors</h2>
<p>There are many different types of capacitors available, each with its own unique characteristics. Some common types include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Aluminum electrolytic capacitors: These capacitors have a high capacitance and are commonly used in power supplies and audio equipment.</li>
<li>Ceramic capacitors: These capacitors have a low cost and are commonly used in circuits where a small value of capacitance is needed.</li>
<li>Film capacitors: These capacitors have a high dielectric strength and are commonly used in high voltage and high frequency applications.</li>
<li>Supercapacitors: These capacitors have a very high capacitance and can store a large amount of energy. They are commonly used in applications such as energy storage and backup power.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="uses-of-capacitors">Uses of Capacitors</h2>
<p>Capacitors are used in a wide variety of applications, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Power supplies: Capacitors are used to smooth out the output of power supplies and to filter out unwanted noise.</li>
<li>Audio equipment: Capacitors are used in audio equipment to block DC signals and to allow AC signals to pass through.</li>
<li>Motor controls: Capacitors are used in motor controls to provide a &ldquo;boost&rdquo; of energy to start the motor.</li>
<li>Signal processing: Capacitors are used in signal processing circuits to filter out unwanted signals and to adjust the phase of signals.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="charging-and-discharging-a-capacitor">Charging and Discharging a Capacitor</h2>
<p>When a capacitor is connected to a voltage source, an electric field is established between the plates of the capacitor, which causes charges to accumulate on the plates. The amount of charge that accumulates on the plates is directly proportional to the voltage applied to the capacitor. This process is known as charging the capacitor.</p>
<p>The rate at which a capacitor charges depends on the capacitance and the resistance in the circuit. The capacitance of the capacitor determines how much charge it can store for a given voltage, and the resistance in the circuit determines how quickly the charges can flow to the capacitor.</p>
<p>When a capacitor is disconnected from a voltage source, the charges on the plates will begin to flow back to the circuit, and the voltage across the capacitor will decrease. This process is known as discharging the capacitor. The rate of discharging also depends on the capacitance and the resistance in the circuit. A capacitor can be charged and discharged many times and it will not lose its capacitance.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UMHSMJmYJdY" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>In this video, we can see how a capacitor behaves when charging and discharging.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Capacitors are essential components in many electrical circuits, and they play an important role in many applications. Understanding how capacitors work and how they are used can help you to design and build more efficient and reliable circuits.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Study of Dmm</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-dmm/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:26:51 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-dmm/</guid><description>Summary This topic aims to provide an in-depth understanding of digital multimeters, including its construction, components, and various applications.
Diagram Basic DMM Parts and Specifications Part Specification Display LCD or LED Range Selection Manual or Auto Ranging Input Impedance &amp;gt;10 MΩ Maximum Voltage 600V AC/DC Maximum Current 10A AC/DC Resistance 200Ω to 200MΩ Continuity Test Built-in Buzzer Diode Test Built-in Tools and Instruments Digital multimeter Lead set 9V battery Circuit under test Procedure The procedure for using a digital multimeter is quite straightforward.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>This topic aims to provide an in-depth understanding of digital multimeters, including its construction, components, and various applications.</p>
<h2 id="diagram">Diagram</h2>
<figure><img src="/img/dmm.jpg"/><figcaption>
            <h4>Basic DMM</h4>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="parts-and-specifications">Parts and Specifications</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Part</th>
<th>Specification</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Display</td>
<td>LCD or LED</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Range Selection</td>
<td>Manual or Auto Ranging</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Input Impedance</td>
<td>&gt;10 MΩ</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maximum Voltage</td>
<td>600V AC/DC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Maximum Current</td>
<td>10A AC/DC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Resistance</td>
<td>200Ω to 200MΩ</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Continuity Test</td>
<td>Built-in Buzzer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Diode Test</td>
<td>Built-in</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="tools-and-instruments">Tools and Instruments</h2>
<ul>
<li>Digital multimeter</li>
<li>Lead set</li>
<li>9V battery</li>
<li>Circuit under test</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="procedure">Procedure</h2>
<p>The procedure for using a digital multimeter is quite straightforward. First, select the appropriate range for the measurement to be taken. Then, connect the leads to the multimeter and to the circuit under test. Finally, observe the reading on the display. It is important to note that the polarity of the leads should be observed, as some measurements require the leads to be connected in a specific way.</p>
<h2 id="theory">Theory</h2>
<p>A digital multimeter is an electronic measuring instrument that can measure several electrical parameters such as voltage, current, resistance, and continuity. Digital multimeters use an ADC (Analog-to-Digital Converter) to convert the analog signals into digital signals for display on a screen.</p>
<p>The input impedance of a digital multimeter is high, typically above 10 MΩ, which means that it has very little effect on the circuit being measured. This is important because it allows accurate measurements to be taken without disturbing the circuit under test.</p>
<h2 id="types-of-digital-multimeters">Types of Digital Multimeters</h2>
<p>There are two main types of digital multimeters: manual ranging and auto ranging. Manual ranging multimeters require the user to select the appropriate range for the measurement, while auto-ranging multimeters automatically select the correct range.</p>
<p>Another type of digital multimeter is handheld multimeters, which are compact and portable, and can be easily carried to the work site. Benchtop multimeters, on the other hand, are larger in size and are designed to be used in a laboratory or workshop setting.</p>
<h2 id="applications">Applications</h2>
<p>Digital multimeters are widely used in a variety of industries, including electronics, electrical, and automotive. They can be used for troubleshooting and repairing electronic circuits, as well as for testing and measuring various electrical parameters in a circuit. Digital multimeters are also commonly used in educational settings for teaching electronics and electrical principles.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In conclusion, digital multimeters are an essential tool for anyone involved in the field of electronics and electrical work. They are versatile, accurate, and provide quick and reliable measurements, making them an indispensable tool for professionals and hobbyists alike.</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>