<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Electronics-1 on Atharva Phadke</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/electronics/11th/electronics-1/</link><description>Recent content in Electronics-1 on Atharva Phadke</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>CC BY-NC 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 22:44:41 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/electronics/11th/electronics-1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Study of Resistors</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-resistors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 05:13:36 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-resistors/</guid><description>Study Of Resistors Part 1: Study of Resistors Aim The aim of this section is to provide a comprehensive understanding of resistors, their components, equipments, and types.
Components List Resistor Multimeter Equipments Power Supply Breadboard Types Of Resistors Fixed Resistors Variable Resistors Information about Fixed Resistors Fixed resistors are electrical components that have a fixed value of resistance, meaning that their resistance does not change. This type of resistor is commonly used to limit the current flow in a circuit and to divide voltage.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="study-of-resistors">Study Of Resistors</h1>
<h2 id="part-1-study-of-resistors">Part 1: Study of Resistors</h2>
<h3 id="aim">Aim</h3>
<p>The aim of this section is to provide a comprehensive understanding of resistors, their components, equipments, and types.</p>
<h3 id="components-list">Components List</h3>
<ol>
<li>Resistor</li>
<li>Multimeter</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="equipments">Equipments</h3>
<ol>
<li>Power Supply</li>
<li>Breadboard</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="types-of-resistors">Types Of Resistors</h3>
<ol>
<li>Fixed Resistors</li>
<li>Variable Resistors</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="information-about-fixed-resistors">Information about Fixed Resistors</h3>
<p>Fixed resistors are electrical components that have a fixed value of resistance, meaning that their resistance does not change. This type of resistor is commonly used to limit the current flow in a circuit and to divide voltage.</p>
<h3 id="information-about-different-types-of-fixed-resistors">Information about different types of Fixed Resistors</h3>
<ol>
<li>Carbon Film Resistor: These resistors are made by depositing a thin layer of carbon on a cylindrical ceramic or plastic form. They are the most common type of fixed resistor and offer a low cost solution with a relatively high resistance tolerance.</li>
<li>Metal Film Resistor: These resistors are made by depositing a thin layer of metal on a cylindrical ceramic or plastic form. They offer improved resistance tolerance compared to carbon film resistors and are more stable.</li>
<li>Wire Wound Resistor: These resistors are made by winding a wire, typically made of nickel-chromium alloy, around a cylindrical form. They offer high power handling capabilities and precise resistance values, making them suitable for use in high-power applications.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="resistor-colour-coding">Resistor Colour Coding</h3>
<p><img src="https://www.te.com/content/dam/te-com/images/corporate/marketing/global/infographics/resistor-color-code-bands-3-4-1024.png" alt="Resistor Colour Coding"></p>
<h3 id="information-about-variable-resistors">Information about Variable Resistors</h3>
<p>Variable resistors, also known as potentiometers, allow the resistance value to be adjusted. They are commonly used in applications where the resistance value needs to be changed, such as volume control in a stereo system.</p>
<h3 id="information-about-different-types-of-variable-resistors">Information about different types of Variable Resistors</h3>
<ol>
<li>Potentiometer: A potentiometer is a three-terminal resistor where the resistance between two terminals can be adjusted using a sliding contact known as a wiper.</li>
<li>Rheostat: A rheostat is a two-terminal resistor where the resistance can be adjusted using a sliding contact. Rheostats are typically used to control the current flow in a circuit.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="part-2-potential-divider-arrangement">Part 2: Potential divider arrangement</h2>
<h3 id="aim-1">Aim</h3>
<p>The aim of this section is to study the potential divider arrangement in detail and understand its applications in electronics.</p>
<h3 id="components-list-1">Components List</h3>
<ol>
<li>Resistor</li>
<li>Voltage Source</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="equipments-1">Equipments</h3>
<ol>
<li>Breadboard</li>
<li>Multimeter</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="explain-theory-in-deep">Explain theory in deep</h3>
<p>In a potential divider arrangement, two resistors are connected in series to a voltage source. The voltage across each resistor is proportional to its resistance, with the voltage across the first resistor (R1) being Vout and the voltage across the second resistor (R2) being (Vin - Vout). By knowing the voltage across the resistors, the resistance values can be calculated using Ohm&rsquo;s law, which states that the current in a circuit is equal to the voltage divided by the resistance.</p>
<h3 id="diagram">Diagram</h3>
<p><img src="https://qph.cf2.quoracdn.net/main-qimg-3ada7a203f51881e291de1e7d67daa99" alt="Potential divider arrangement diagram"></p>
<h3 id="formula-for-potential-divider-arrangement">Formula for potential divider arrangement</h3>
<p>Vout = (R2/(R1 + R2)) * Vin</p>
<h3 id="example">Example</h3>
<p>Given Vin = 10V and R1 = 2kΩ and R2 = 4kΩ, find Vout.</p>
<p>Vout = (R2/(R1 + R2)) * Vin
Vout = (4kΩ/(2kΩ + 4kΩ)) * 10V
Vout = (4kΩ/6kΩ) * 10V
Vout = (2/3) * 10V
Vout = 6.67V</p>
<p>For Notes, and practical images, refer this:
<a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/11ARyTZphPKpo9fPhy97rB0HLTRN2Exp5?usp=sharing"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Drive-Folder-green" alt="GDrive Folder"></a></p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>In this study, we have covered the basics of resistors, including their components, types, and the potential divider arrangement. Understanding resistors and their behavior is crucial in many electrical and electronics applications.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Construction of Ce Amp on Breadboard</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-ce-amp-on-breadboard/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:31:48 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-ce-amp-on-breadboard/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Construction of Multivibrator Ckt on Pcb</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multivibrator-ckt-on-pcb/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:31:25 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multivibrator-ckt-on-pcb/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Construction of Fbr With Filter</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-fbr-with-filter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:30:59 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-fbr-with-filter/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Loading Effect of Voltmeter</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/loading-effect-of-voltmeter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:29:52 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/loading-effect-of-voltmeter/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Construction of Multirange Ammeter</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multirange-ammeter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:29:33 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multirange-ammeter/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Construction of Multirange Voltmeter</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multirange-voltmeter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:29:22 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/construction-of-multirange-voltmeter/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Sinusoidal Non Sinusoidal Waveforms on Cro</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-sinusoidal-non-sinusoidal-waveforms-on-cro/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:28:58 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-sinusoidal-non-sinusoidal-waveforms-on-cro/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Mpt Theorem</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/mpt-theorem/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:28:20 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/mpt-theorem/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Thevenin's Theorem</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-thevenins-theorem/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:54 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-thevenins-theorem/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Transformer</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-transformer/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:35 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-transformer/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Relay</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-relay/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-relay/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Switches</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-switches/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:19 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-switches/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item><item><title>Study of Inductors</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-inductors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:08 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-inductors/</guid><description>An inductor is a passive electrical component that stores energy in a magnetic field when electric current flows through it. Inductors play a crucial role in many electrical circuits, from filtering to energy storage to regulation. In this study, we will delve into the construction, theory, and uses of inductors.
Construction of a Basic Air-Core Inductor The basic air-core inductor can be constructed by wrapping a wire around a non-conductive core, such as air, plastic, or fiberglass.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An inductor is a passive electrical component that stores energy in a magnetic field when electric current flows through it. Inductors play a crucial role in many electrical circuits, from filtering to energy storage to regulation. In this study, we will delve into the construction, theory, and uses of inductors.</p>
<h2 id="construction-of-a-basic-air-core-inductor">Construction of a Basic Air-Core Inductor</h2>
<p>The basic air-core inductor can be constructed by wrapping a wire around a non-conductive core, such as air, plastic, or fiberglass. The number of turns, or coils, of wire used, along with the diameter and material of the wire, will determine the inductance of the inductor. To calculate the inductance, the formula <code>L = N^2 * Μ_o * A / l</code> can be used, where <code>N</code> is the number of turns, <code>Μ_o</code> is the permeability of free space, <code>A</code> is the cross-sectional area of the coil, and <code>l</code> is the length of the coil.</p>
<p><img src="https://circuitdigest.com/sites/default/files/inlineimages/u1/Passive-Inductor.png" alt="Diagram"></p>
<p>Diagram: A simple representation of an air-core inductor</p>
<h2 id="parts-and-specifications">Parts and Specifications</h2>
<p>The following table lists the parts and specifications needed to construct a basic air-core inductor:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Parts</th>
<th>Specifications</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Wire</td>
<td>Enameled copper wire with a diameter of 0.5 mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Core</td>
<td>Non-conductive material, such as air or plastic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Insulation tape</td>
<td>Electrical insulating tape to secure the ends of the wire</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="instruments-equipments-and-tools">Instruments, Equipments, and Tools</h2>
<p>To construct an air-core inductor, you will need the following instruments, equipments, and tools:</p>
<ul>
<li>A wire stripper</li>
<li>A spool of enameled copper wire</li>
<li>A non-conductive core, such as air or plastic</li>
<li>Electrical insulating tape</li>
<li>A ruler or measuring tape</li>
<li>A calculator</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="procedure">Procedure</h2>
<p>The procedure for constructing a basic air-core inductor involves wrapping a wire around a non-conductive core and securing the ends of the wire. The steps for this procedure are explained in detail below:</p>
<ol>
<li>Determine the desired inductance and calculate the number of turns required.</li>
<li>Cut a length of enameled copper wire to the desired length, plus an extra 10 cm for securing the ends.</li>
<li>Strip the insulation from the ends of the wire.</li>
<li>Wrap the wire around the non-conductive core to the desired number of turns.</li>
<li>Secure the ends of the wire with electrical insulating tape.</li>
<li>Test the inductance using a multimeter.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="theory">Theory</h2>
<p>An inductor is a passive electrical component that stores energy in a magnetic field when electric current flows through it. The basic principle behind an inductor is Faraday&rsquo;s Law of Electromagnetic Induction, which states that a changing magnetic field induces an electromotive force (EMF) in a conductor. The amount of energy stored in an inductor is proportional to the number of turns in the wire and the current flowing through it.</p>
<h2 id="types-of-cores">Types of Cores</h2>
<p>There are several different types of cores that can be used in inductors, including air cores, iron cores, ferrite cores, and more. Each type of core has its own unique properties and advantages, making it ideal for specific applications.</p>
<p>Air cores are the simplest and most basic type of inductor core, and are ideal for applications that require a large inductance. They are also the most economical and easiest to manufacture.</p>
<p>Iron cores are used for high-frequency applications and provide a higher magnetic permeability than air cores. They also allow for a more compact design, as the magnetic field is concentrated in the core.</p>
<p>Ferrite cores are made of a magnetic ceramic material and are often used in high-frequency applications where a high impedance is required. They are also immune to temperature changes, making them ideal for use in temperature-sensitive applications.</p>
<h3 id="uses-of-inductor">Uses of Inductor</h3>
<p>Inductors are widely used in electrical circuits for various purposes, including power supplies, filters, transformers, and resonant circuits.</p>
<p>One of the most common uses of inductors is in filters. Inductors are used in filter circuits to block or pass certain frequencies. A high-pass filter passes high-frequency signals and blocks low-frequency signals, while a low-pass filter passes low-frequency signals and blocks high-frequency signals.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>In conclusion, Inductors are important components in electrical circuits, and understanding their construction, parts, instruments, procedure, theory, types of cores, and uses is crucial. With this knowledge, one can effectively design and implement inductors in various electrical circuits.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Study of Capacitors</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-capacitors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-capacitors/</guid><description>Understanding Capacitors: A Study A capacitor is an electronic component that stores electrical energy in an electric field. Capacitors are widely used in electrical circuits for a variety of purposes, including filtering, coupling, and energy storage.
Types of Capacitors There are many different types of capacitors available, each with its own unique characteristics. Some common types include:
Aluminum electrolytic capacitors: These capacitors have a high capacitance and are commonly used in power supplies and audio equipment.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="understanding-capacitors-a-study">Understanding Capacitors: A Study</h1>
<p>A capacitor is an electronic component that stores electrical energy in an electric field. Capacitors are widely used in electrical circuits for a variety of purposes, including filtering, coupling, and energy storage.</p>
<h2 id="types-of-capacitors">Types of Capacitors</h2>
<p>There are many different types of capacitors available, each with its own unique characteristics. Some common types include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Aluminum electrolytic capacitors: These capacitors have a high capacitance and are commonly used in power supplies and audio equipment.</li>
<li>Ceramic capacitors: These capacitors have a low cost and are commonly used in circuits where a small value of capacitance is needed.</li>
<li>Film capacitors: These capacitors have a high dielectric strength and are commonly used in high voltage and high frequency applications.</li>
<li>Supercapacitors: These capacitors have a very high capacitance and can store a large amount of energy. They are commonly used in applications such as energy storage and backup power.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="uses-of-capacitors">Uses of Capacitors</h2>
<p>Capacitors are used in a wide variety of applications, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Power supplies: Capacitors are used to smooth out the output of power supplies and to filter out unwanted noise.</li>
<li>Audio equipment: Capacitors are used in audio equipment to block DC signals and to allow AC signals to pass through.</li>
<li>Motor controls: Capacitors are used in motor controls to provide a &ldquo;boost&rdquo; of energy to start the motor.</li>
<li>Signal processing: Capacitors are used in signal processing circuits to filter out unwanted signals and to adjust the phase of signals.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="charging-and-discharging-a-capacitor">Charging and Discharging a Capacitor</h2>
<p>When a capacitor is connected to a voltage source, an electric field is established between the plates of the capacitor, which causes charges to accumulate on the plates. The amount of charge that accumulates on the plates is directly proportional to the voltage applied to the capacitor. This process is known as charging the capacitor.</p>
<p>The rate at which a capacitor charges depends on the capacitance and the resistance in the circuit. The capacitance of the capacitor determines how much charge it can store for a given voltage, and the resistance in the circuit determines how quickly the charges can flow to the capacitor.</p>
<p>When a capacitor is disconnected from a voltage source, the charges on the plates will begin to flow back to the circuit, and the voltage across the capacitor will decrease. This process is known as discharging the capacitor. The rate of discharging also depends on the capacitance and the resistance in the circuit. A capacitor can be charged and discharged many times and it will not lose its capacitance.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UMHSMJmYJdY" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p>In this video, we can see how a capacitor behaves when charging and discharging.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Capacitors are essential components in many electrical circuits, and they play an important role in many applications. Understanding how capacitors work and how they are used can help you to design and build more efficient and reliable circuits.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Study of Dmm</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-dmm/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:26:51 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-dmm/</guid><description/><content type="html"></content></item></channel></rss>