<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Atharva Phadke</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Atharva Phadke</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>CC BY-NC 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 18:00:32 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://atharvap8.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Esp32 Washing Machine</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2024/06/esp32-washing-machine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 18:00:32 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2024/06/esp32-washing-machine/</guid><description>Coming SOON!</description></item><item><title>Alexa Washing Machine</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2024/06/alexa-washing-machine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 17:57:12 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2024/06/alexa-washing-machine/</guid><description>Coming SOON!</description></item><item><title>Automatic Water Tap V2</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2024/06/automatic-water-tap-v2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 12:57:02 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2024/06/automatic-water-tap-v2/</guid><description>Introduction In this project, I have built an IR Sensor-based automatic water tap. This system allows water to flow when it detects an object in front of the sensor, making it a convenient and hygienic solution for home or public restrooms. The IR sensor is mounted on the tap head to detect any objects near the water tap.
Components Required IR Sensor Module 12V Solenoid Valve PNP Transistor: BD140 Resistor: 10kΩ, 1/4Watt, ±5% Diode: 1N4007 General Purpose Diode Power Supply (230V AC to 12V DC) Mini 360 Buck Converter D4184 Mosfet Control Module Connecting Wires Enclosure Screws, Zip Ties, Piping, etc.</description></item><item><title>About me, and this website</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/about/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m Atharva Phadke, trying to understand how basic and complicated systems/machines/objects work in real life. Always likes to dissect everything, and get to the root.
I know quite about Electronics, you can ask related doubts on: &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</description></item><item><title>Study of Resistors</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-resistors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 05:13:36 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-resistors/</guid><description>Study Of Resistors Basic Resistor Diagram: A basic resistor. Part 1: Study of Resistors Working of Resistor Aim The aim of this section is to provide a comprehensive understanding of resistors, their components, equipments, and types.
Components List Resistor Multimeter Equipments Power Supply Breadboard Types Of Resistors Fixed Resistors Variable Resistors Information about Fixed Resistors Fixed resistors are electrical components that have a fixed value of resistance, meaning that their resistance does not change.</description></item><item><title>Testing of Diodes and Transistors</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/testing-of-diodes-and-transistors/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:39:28 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/testing-of-diodes-and-transistors/</guid><description>Aim The aim of this study is to understand the methods of testing diodes and transistors and to identify the working and faulty components.
Components Required Component Description Diodes Any standard diode Transistors Any NPN or PNP transistor Resistor Any value between 1kΩ to 10kΩ Multimeter Digital multimeter with diode and transistor testing function Equipments Needed Breadboard Jumper Wires Theory Diode Testing A diode is a two-terminal electronic component that allows current to flow in only one direction.</description></item><item><title>Study of HWR and FWR Using CT Transformer</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-hwr-and-fwr-using-ct-transformer/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:38:33 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-hwr-and-fwr-using-ct-transformer/</guid><description>Part-1: Study of Half-Wave Rectifier Aim To study the half-wave rectifier and its input and output waveform.
Components Required Component Quantity Diode 1 Resistor 1 Capacitor 1 Transformer 1 Power Supply 1 Equipment Required Oscilloscope Function Generator Breadboard Connecting Wires Circuit Diagram 👇🏻 Theory The half-wave rectifier is a simple circuit that converts AC voltage into a pulsating DC voltage. It consists of a diode that is connected in series with the load resistor and an AC source.</description></item><item><title>Transistor as a Switch</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/transistor-as-a-switch/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:35:08 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/transistor-as-a-switch/</guid><description>Aim The aim of this study is to understand the working of a transistor as a switch and how it can be used to control the flow of current in a circuit.
Components Required Component Description Transistor Any NPN or PNP transistor Resistor Any value between 1kΩ to 10kΩ LED Any standard LED Power Supply Any DC power supply with voltage between 5V to 12V Equipments Needed Breadboard Jumper Wires Multimeter Theory A transistor can be used as a switch to control the flow of current in a circuit.</description></item><item><title>Study of Bridge Rectifier</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-bridge-rectifier/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:33:03 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-bridge-rectifier/</guid><description>Aim The aim of this study is to understand the working of a bridge rectifier and to observe its input and output waveforms.
Components Required Component Quantity Diode 4 Resistor 4 Capacitor 1 Transformer 1 Equipments Needed Digital multimeter Function generator Oscilloscope Connecting wires Theory A bridge rectifier is an electronic circuit that converts an alternating current (AC) input into a direct current (DC) output. The rectifier circuit consists of four diodes arranged in a bridge configuration.</description></item><item><title>Study of Transformer</title><link>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-transformer/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:27:35 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://atharvap8.github.io/posts/2023/01/study-of-transformer/</guid><description>Summary A transformer is a passive electrical component that transfers electrical energy from one circuit to another through electromagnetic induction. In this study, we will learn about the construction and working of a basic transformer, different types of transformers, and their applications. We will also learn about the parts required to make a basic transformer and the instruments and equipment needed to perform this activity.
Basic Transformer Parts and Specifications A basic transformer consists of the following parts:</description></item></channel></rss>